# Ammar Rehan Toronto, ON

Data Engineer | BI Developer | Software Developer | Electrical Engineer

Email: work@.ammarrehan.live

LinkedIn: https://ca.linkedin.com/in/ammar-rehan

Website: <a href="https://ammarrehan.live">https://ammarrehan.live</a>

Trained as an electrical engineer, I am an IT professional with about 3 years of experience in diverse projects, including database design, data warehousing, ETL, data visualization, BI, consulting, and product development. Passionate about learning, structuring and extracting insights from data.

#### **SKILLS**

Languages: Python, DAX, T-SQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL, C, C++, Excel VBA, Shell

Software: SSMS, SSIS, Docker, Heroku, MS Power BI, Proxmox, Linux Server, MongoDB, dbt,

MS Azure Portal/ ADF, WordPress, MATLAB, Git, JIRA, Trello, Asana, ClickUp

Soft Skills: Critical Thinking, Adaptive/flexible, Resourceful, Organized, Communication,

Observant

Certifications: Azure Fundamentals, Azure Data Fundamentals, 365DataScience

**Expertise:** Database design/modelling, **Data management/validation**, **Data warehousing**,

SQL Views/SP/Jobs, **SQL/NoSQL**, Web Automation, **Spark**, **CI/CD**, BI development, **OOP/MVC**, **Back-end Development**, Machine Learning, Containerization, Project management, Product development, Consulting, Academic Research, Kanban, Scrum

#### **RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Technology Consultant, Rehan Mobin & Co- Remote**

Feb 2022 – Present

- Developed desktop **python** application to automate data entry reducing report uploading times by over 80%. Application was based on **MVC framework**, with GUI views for getting and validating user input, web-scraping to gather relevant information and web-drivers for form entry and picture uploads.
- Setup **software delivery** on custom **domain** and launched software for over 50 users spread across 5 locations.
- Deployed **Proxmox server** with static IP and port forwarding to allow **remote access** to development environment and backup management.

## Data Engineer, HashMove- Dubai, UAE

Aug 2021 – Mar 2022

- **Constructed data warehouse** by amalgamating order and administrative data from various **OLTP** sources, optimizing it for operational management and **analytics**.
- Developed **web scraping bot** using selenium (**python**) for extracting freight forwarder contact information from their websites accessed via online directories. This information was integrated into mailing lists and forwarders were contacted regarding specific customer queries.
- Developed **ETL pipeline** using SQL Server Integration Services (**SSIS**) to automate web scraping, data transformation and loading data into data **warehouse**.
- Developed **views** combining data from multiple master tables in the data warehouse which improved BI data modeling, query plans and query timings resulting in **faster BI** dashboard **performance**.
- Developed stored procedures and scheduled jobs to routinely transfer data from OLTP databases to data warehouses.

### BI Developer, HashMove- Dubai, UAE

**Apr 2021 – Mar 2022** 

- Designed and developed **BI dashboards** using complex data models and custom themes and visuals- for company management (CRM/CPM), clients and partners (**analytics**). Embedded these dashboards into the HashMove web app.
- Developed **real-time** (Direct Query) **dashboards** utilizing optimized data models which were used by operations and support teams for live engagement with clients and partners.
- **Analyzed DAX query plans** and server timings on DAX studio to **improve** DAX **query performance** and optimize data models, improving dashboard performance.
- Performed **data wrangling** on data warehouse detecting **anomalies** and **exposing validation issues** within the data pipeline.

#### IT Consultant- Vancouver, BC

May 2020 - Apr 2021

- Developed static WordPress website and hosted it at no cost, on GitHub pages.
- Setup **Cloudflare** on domain for security and optimizing website performance.
- Setup **business emails** and **CRM** for business organization using Zoho suite.
- Created **ERDs** for a web application, identifying performance **bottlenecks** and **suggested optimizations** which resulted in a more scalable application.

## Consulting Engineer, TECHPOS- Vancouver, BC

**Sep 2019 – May 2020** 

- Developed **wireless communication framework** in **python** based on the request-response protocol to allow secure data exchange between and edge device and multiple paired IoT end devices utilizing the ZigBee spectrum.
- Developed **python**-based **configuration interface** to facilitate wireless communication including addition of end devices to network, edge device configuration, and remote configuration of end devices.
- Ensured timely development of software and prototypes adhering to **waterfall** approach. Used **Asana** for project portfolio management and delivered MVP to company on time.
- Assisted in development of multiple prototype devices using 3D modelling software and conducted prototype testing.

#### Research Assistant, CFET Lab, UBC- Vancouver, BC

Jun – Aug 2019

- Implemented **cloud-based data collection and management** process which increased researcher collaboration and virtually eliminated data loss.
- Reduced stack production failure rate by over 50% by developing **python** application for precise **servomotor control** and **auto-focus** of monolayers under microscope using **OpenCV**.
- Experimented with different exfoliation techniques increasing production of isolated monolayers of 2D materials (Graphene/ Tungsten Diselenide/ etc.) by over 20%.

#### **EDUCATION**

## The University of British Columbia, Vancouver

**Sep 2015 – May 2020** 

Bachelor of Applied Science in Electrical Engineering

- Recipient of Outstanding International Student Award worth \$10000.
- Recipient of Chancellors Scholar Award.

**Interests:** Hiking/Camping, Trading/Investing, Hobby-coding, Running, Yoga, Cooking